In this video I will tell you my story,
how I learned coding by myself and how
I took the job of a software engineer
and why I left my school and college studies after 10th.
Yes, after 10th I only studied in 11th.
After that, I did
not complete any formal education, yet
I have been working as a software engineer for 3 years,
so I will tell you this whole story and
how you too can learn regardless of
your qualification or your
background.
can also become a coder, you can become a software engineer
and you can also get a job, so
first let me introduce myself,
my name is Anurag Singh and I
am a software engineer. For the last 3 years,
I have been working as an engineer in Bangalore.
working as a software engineer. The name of the first company I joined
was Digit Insurance. Now
I work remotely for a UK based company.
I come from a small village named
Birwa Bhani in UP, which is in Gonda district.
am near Ayodhya and
I have been there for the last one and a half year.
I have created a complete course on front end development
which you will get on youtube's. In
it in the form of a playlist,
I covered every single thing which is
required in front end.
many children have studied from it and they
also got jobs and many children are studying every day,
watch and comment every day, they like the
course and my family
background is of agriculture, my father,
my grandfather, everyone was a farmer and I.
farming with them, used to go to the fields, used to do
all the work of the farm,
although I, my father used to
drive the car along with farming, he was also a driver
and my education is from one to eight.
My education till then was in Hindi medium.
I studied in Hindi medium first from class one to
five in Saraswati Shishu Mandir, then from
six to eight I studied in a government school
and I had a lot of interest in science from the beginning
because when we used to sleep at night.
My father used to sleep on the terrace, used to
talk about aliens, used to talk about other planets, used to talk about
many things, how is day and night on earth, used to
talk about all these things, so I
had a lot of interest in science, that is
why I used to read my syllabus book.
I used to read other books which were any science
books. When I was in eighth six seventh eighth,
I used to
read science books of class 10th on demand, I used to
bring books of my cousins ​​and I used to
read from them.
is, I used to get good marks in the middle of 7080.
I never topped and there was no pressure from my house
either from father or mother, we just used to
study.
and whatever interested us, whatever we liked,
we used to study the same and then in the middle,
I started getting very interested in Maths. The
reason for getting interested in Maths was one of
our Sonu Bhaiya, he took a lot of
interest in my Maths.
that we can measure the height of the tree we are looking at without
climbing it. How can we measure the height of the tree with the help of Maths? There is
a trigonometry in Maths,
after that I started getting
very interested in Maths too. I felt that it was
real.
so I got interested in science and maths
because of my father, I got interested in maths
because of Sonu Bhaiya, then both of them
were my favorite subjects, I always used to
study them and also got good marks in the class.
pass, meaning there was no bad
student, there was no very good student
but I used to pass,
my third and fourth rank in the class was like this, I
never even got second, I only got
third, fourth or fifth like this.
and no one has any problem, I used to
study comfortably, what happened once was that
when I was in 8th class, I used to come from school,
my bag was on the bicycle and I used to
park the bicycle and then
eat food.
means my bag used to remain attached to the same bicycle.
When my father
saw that my bag remained attached to the bicycle for many days, the
bag itself did not come off, then he said
that the bagwa should not be taken off.
period language, in that language
they said that you don't take off your bag, what do you
mean don't you read? Did I say I read?
Secondly, I mean I have asked for the books of Akash bhaiya and Ashish
bhaiya, I
basically read those books of ours.
means cousin, so I used to read his books on
science and maths. He said ok,
no problem, this was the situation, that is, I
was not even touched by school, so
my English was not good in earth class, I basically
studied in Hindi medium.
like every Hindi medium student
has, similarly I also had English. Then what
happened was that once it was Republic Day in our school
or I think it must have been 15th August
or 26th January, then a friend in it
said let's go next door.
where it is a very good school. Let's
go and see it. So, I went with him to
see it there on 15th August. I found the school
very big, I liked it very much and it
was an English medium school and we
didn't even know about it.
distance of 45 kilometers 34 kilometers from us, so
I told at home that I want to
study in an English medium school, then mother talked to father,
then father took me and my sister
on a bicycle and took me there.
And I said that he has already
passed 8th class. I had passed 8th
in Hindi medium. He said
that you should take admission in 8th again
or study again. Then he said
first or second class.
Gave me a science book and said, read this and see what is
written in it. I was
not able to read even a single word of it. Just
this is M is this. I was able to read only these words which are of two or three letters. They were
important.
he said that it is not possible for him to get
admission in Hindi English medium,
so I said that he should do it
in the seventh class, he said, it is
not possible, that is, it is not a first class
book.
how will this work be done? They are
not able to read books of first class only, all the
children can read easily, so I said,
you take me in seventh class, I will work
very hard, I will study day and night.
learn to read English, he said
no, meaning it is not possible, I said, you
take me in the sixth class, he accepted the
defeat and said, okay, I will take
admission in the sixth class, so I got
admission in the sixth class and I am in
my class.
I was the first boy in the village to go to an English medium school. When I went there,
all the children, that is, everyone knew English,
everyone could write and
read very easily, no one spoke it, everyone
spoke in Hindi but at least
read less books and used to write. When the teacher
spoke, I used to note it down. I did
not know it, so I worked very
hard, bought a lot of dictionaries and learned a lot.
Gradually, within a year,
I became English meaning.
I reached the level where I could read and write, I worked very hard
and then I became at par with all the students. By the time
I was in seventh grade,
my maths, Hindi and other
subjects like science were quite good, so they were
not as good as those people.
studied till A so I already knew all the
things. I could solve Maths very easily.
Hindi was from Hindi medium so
Hindi was good and the rest of the subjects
were quite good for me just because of English.
That was also a problem and in one year I had
done English well and had made it at
par with them, then in seventh I worked harder and
got a little better. Then in Earth
I did an English course, an English
speaking course, which helped me to improve my English speaking skills.
came to know English well, meaning in a way,
I started writing down whatever I could think in my mind, so
I read Six Seven Eighth twice, once in
Hindi medium, once in English medium
and when I was in Earth and then after that
in ninth grade, my father asked me,
'What are you going to become? I had
no idea, I thought becoming a scientist or an
astronaut is what everyone has, it is
a dream. He said that
software engineer is a great job.
You try to
see how one becomes a software engineer and what one has to study.
From there I came to know that there is
something like a software engineer and this is how they came to know
that the one whose car he used to drive was a
driver and the children of those who used to drive his car were
software engineers.
he came to know that a software engineer has a
good job and a good salary,
so he said that an engineer's
job is good, try it, you
see, I said, okay, we will see, then
I will be in the ninth.
admission in ninth class. There was no college in the village,
no school. Basically, we had to
come to the city. After coming to the city, my
father got me admitted in the school and at that time, my
father's salary was Rs. 5000 and my salary was Rs. 5000.
fee was Rs 1500, meaning the school
fee was Rs 00, then when I did coaching,
two and a half rupees were spent on my studies,
half my salary was spent on my studies
and then it was around Rs 12 1 or 14
15.
so
I studied like this in ninth and 10th and
when I finished my 10th by giving exams,
my father met with an accident
and was returning home after doing his duty.
about 2 kilometers away from home, he had an
accident with his bike, he was hit by some vehicle
and then he passed by. When
I went there, I
mean, there was no scratch on his body, but
his
touching the chest, it felt as if there
was a stomach, meaning there were no bones there.
Then they took him to the hospital, there was no use, they
just took him and I was there, meaning I did
n't cry, I couldn't cry.
I cry, what will happen to my mother, my siblings
because at that time I
was the oldest male in my family, my
grandfather had already passed out two-three
years ago and I was the eldest male.
I thought, don't cry, I was feeling like crying
but still I was controlling
myself, then I thought
what to do now, there is nothing, now I
won't even be able to study, but still my mother told
me.
my father's responsibility, she took
up it. She used to work as an Asha Asha worker and whatever
money she got from doing Hajj, she did
not get more than this, she took care of my education,
household expenses and our farm.
gave it on lease, basically the farm is given on lease like this, we get
some money in a year,
203 thousand rupees were earned in a year, so we
gave the farm on lease and
father had some money from LIC, which
is work.
so I went to school in 11th also, the same
school, yes but no, I studied 10th,
I used to go to school in 11th also and we had a sir,
Rupesh sir, when he came to know that my
father.
math coaching. Earlier too, I used to study from them only.
They made my math coaching
free, but the school
fees were to be paid by the school and I used to
pay the fees for other coachings.
knew this way that if we want to
become a software engineer then we will have to do IIT, after
IIT then we will have to do B.Tech, only
after that we can dream of becoming a software engineer,
so basically to
do IIT, Physics and Math are important,
very important.
also had interest, I used to study on my own till 10th
and understood everything but
when I went to 11th class,
I was managing Maths, I was able to understand by
studying on my own and
coaching. What does coaching mean? I was learning it on my own
and I mean, one who studied in coaching,
coaching also helped, but I was
not able to understand physics on my own.
I got totally troubled in physics.
Physics was one.
very favorite subject was Physics. I
tried hard to study on my own. I
bought different books. I went to different coaching
institutes.
I went to all the coaching institutes in our district in Gonda, about three-four.
went to institutes where I
thought that someone or the other would teach Physics
but no one was teaching it properly, that
is, everyone was telling that it will
come in your exam and you should focus on it and
it will clear your exam whereas
I had never studied for exams in the beginning
and I could not understand
why we should study for exams, meaning we have to
study to understand, we have to study so
that we can use that thing in our life.
I have tried a lot of things in my life, I
went to a lot of coachings, but I did
not do any workout, no one was able to teach me properly, everyone was
basically teaching me to clear the exams,
which was not my motive, the
exam must be cleared.
understood the exam then I
will definitely crack it, I will crack it at 70-80 marks. I
was so confident. Just explain the topic to me. If
no one could explain then my interest
in studies reduced a lot and that was my only
hope.
then become a software engineer and do B.Tech.
All that started to fade away. Gradually, I
lost interest in studies.
Even after wandering in so many coachings, when I did not understand Physics, no
teacher taught me Physics.
I was feeling very helpless, I was
suddenly broken from within, that is,
I am not able to understand on my own and
no teacher is able to teach me, what should I do now, that is, I
suddenly lost my desire to study.
because I was not able to understand what was my favorite subject, so
somehow I gave the 11th exam and till date
I have not seen the result of the exam. Have
I passed or failed in 11th?
Basically who is in 11th?
might have passed by some marks but I did
not see the result. There was a time when it was like this, that is,
at my house, my mother knew,
my siblings, everyone knew that I was not
studying, I was not going to school,
but
not told anything to my neighbors that I was not
studying or completing 12th.
Then when the 12th exam happened, everyone asked how many
marks I got. I said, I got 70 marks.
I told everyone that I have passed.
but then I thought that I will do it later, I will tell you whether I will
do it from UP board or any government board, then after that
everyone said that mummy said and those who
knew that I did not do it, those people
Said that do it from any medium,
do it from UP board only, then there is
NIOS board, basically like IGNOU,
many people do BCA from IGNOU, then it is open
schooling, similarly there is NIOS board, you have to
fill the form.
submit assignments and that is
online, that is, you learn like this, there is
no class, basically distance
learning, study on your own and after giving the exam,
I filled the form from that, I did
not increase my studies, that means I did not do any study,
my
understand, I was not able to understand, from where I should
study, the same was my favorite subject, I was
not able to understand, what will I do then, what will I do after
studying, so
then I gave the exam for NVS Board.
Gave my 12th exam and this was the first time that
I had failed because I had
not studied anything at all, I just went and gave the exam, the
results of all the subjects except English were
in single digits.
see my 9th and
12th result, basically I
failed, I failed miserably in it,
then the head of Anas Board said that
you fill it with Hindi medium.
Children pass, most of the people pass, everyone
passes. I
filled it in Hindi medium. I filled it in Hindi medium from the board itself and
then gave the exam again.
Same situation happened again only
in some subjects like Hindi and English and
Hindi in it.
which the number was in two digits and in Physics
also the number was in two digits and in all the rest again
in single digit and I
failed again. After that I said
leave it, I will not do all this with my school and
coaching.
told my mother, "Mummy, buy a laptop
for me, I will learn coding and create apps,
I will become an app developer. She
somehow bought a laptop for me. She
collected some money and bought a Dell laptop.
So I thought that
It was on August 10, 2016, when I
got my first laptop. I thought that
in this we will learn coding, we will create an app.
I downloaded And Studio. I came to
know from somewhere that basically a friend of mine
told me that we can learn app development from And Studio.
can do it and my friend was already
doing Diploma in Computer Science,
his name is Faiz, his name is Faiz Ilahi
and today he works with me here in Bangalore,
so he is currently working in my old company.
Said,
install A Studio and we will develop the app. When we
installed it,
its interface was so dangerous, we could not understand anything,
so we thought that we should learn Java language for this. It
was not for Java, so nothing happened, it means we just
installed it.
installed, after that no progress was
made, tried for a month and a half, but
what is half a month, tried only for 1015 days
but nothing happened, means no course was
found, no proper guidance.
what to learn first and what to do later, so I left it, that
too means I uninstalled End Studio
and downloaded A49 game in it,
I used to sit there and play the whole day and
then later the same
friend Faiz himself told me that
Learn C language. At least if you learn C language
then basically it is basic fundamental.
Whatever is the language of a language, everything
starts from C, so he
recommended Saurabh Shukla sir's channel, so
I started watching it, I liked it a lot and
understood programming.
understanding conditional false loops and arrays and all the things, so I learned C from them, I
also learned c+ps and also solved questions which are
questions in DSA type. It was in
2018 when I learned c+ps.
In 2017, I basically played S-Foot
and taught coaching to children and I
worked on my English. I thought that if
nothing else, I would at least improve my English. I used to
watch English videos and
listen to English podcasts, so I
improved my English.
I taught coaching to children and used the laptop only to
play games and
learned the same C again for about a year, after learning C again and
solving the questions, I did not understand
what to do now, that is,
done it, I am also solving the questions,
but will it work? I did not understand anything from this,
then I thought that let's learn web development. It is the
beginning of 2019. I
downloaded some videos. I thought that let's try and
see.
basically one by one tag, they said that
you have to remember this, they were teaching in notepad, they
said that this is the opening tag, this is the closing tag,
in this, you have to put an exclamation
mark, a slash here and there, then you have to
put angular brackets, after seeing that I said.
Web development is better than C language
or web development is the worst thing, I
got this perception after seeing it, I
said, this is just a rote thing, there
is nothing useful in it, otherwise
I left it, I said
not learn development no matter what happens.
It was in 2018 when I
tried web development for the first time and I
lost confidence in it. I thought what to do, you
can't even do development because it
is difficult, there is no one to teach and at that
time.
videos, all the things were very rare at that time, so
I thought what to
do now, I can't even do web development, I ca
n't even do development, what will I do using C, that
means I won't be able to create anything.
some questions but
now I don't feel like solving how much, I do
n't have that much motivation and then I
thought let's go home, there is no point in staying here in the city and
spending money unnecessarily, we will
go home and do farming and
rest.
no problem, all my dreams were shattered, I came home, I
told my mother that I will not do anything now, I will
stay at home, I will just wait and see, whatever
happens, will happen, there was no hope left that if
anything would happen then I
thought that we will open a shop and the
expenses will keep on running. I had thought to such an extent
that now we will do only a shop that
I went beyond the shop of cement and morang sand and
went to that shop.
shop there, that day the
man was not there, that means the shop was closed and there
was only one shop in that area which
was nearby, so I returned, I thought
no problem, we will go the next day.
mood changed, I thought that they do not
do shop, they do some farming, they do farming only a little, they do farming
well, something will happen from farming, they
will do some work in farming, so I used to do
farming, but did
not do it on a very big level.
graze the cow, it was our cow, go and
graze the cow, do farming, cut the wheat, harvest the paddy,
bring it back, a few
laborers used to work, we also did a little
along with us, so this continued and then hope was
lost.
in software, there was no hope
that I would be able to do something like this, then I got
interested in spirituality,
how to control my mind,
how to keep my mind working, although my mind was
already
I didn't get too angry, but even more so, I did
n't care about what others said
because when I was not doing anything,
people started asking, "Brother, what are you doing, what are you going to do, whether you want to do
something or not."
know that he has not even
completed 12th, he has wasted two years and has come here and has taken a
laptop, has taken a mobile,
everyone is getting spoiled, it means
everyone is getting spoiled by having a mobile, and what do
people do?
not, do something, then basically they
also wanted to do something and started saying meaning,
when you don't do anything, sit at home the
whole day, do some outside work, stay at home the
whole day.
watch things related to spirituality. I met
Sadhguru. I liked and understood Sadhguru's words. I
watched all his videos at one time
and by watching those videos, I got the benefit that
I
a great extent. Basically, no matter what anyone
says from outside, it did not make much difference to me.
Earlier too, I did
not get angry, but
now after listening to Sadhguru, it made a difference to
me.
control, my mind started working,
everything was working, it means I started being happy but I was
not doing anything, so there was a wholeness inside, there
was not an amnesiac, but there was a K inside which was
saying that
doing, you will die like this, they came like this
and when I started sitting at home,
one of my acquaintance's brother said that
we have a copper bottle factory, you
pick up the copper bottles from here, we will sell it to you.
give you bottles for ₹ and you sell them at the shop for Rs 250-300, this will make
you some
profit and you will earn something, so I
started doing this, I bought
bottles from them and I took them on a bicycle and used to go from
shop to shop and sell bottles for Rs
250.
asked me to give him 10 bottles,
I will give you some money now and
when all the bottles are sold, I will give you the
money. He gave me Rs. 000,
I also agreed that means I
believed that he will give me the money, it will run away somewhere, he has a
whole shop right here in
our city, so he gave me
Rs. 000, then he said that
we will give him the money after a month, but after a month,
when I asked,
bottles are not being sold, that is, they are being
sold at very low prices, no one is buying them.
I told him, ok,
give me the money for whatever is sold. He gave me
₹ 5000000 for
two-three bottles with him.
returned it and said that brother, that's all
and nothing else would be possible, so the business he had started from there too, which
was a small selling business,
also lost confidence after this incident.
I also stopped selling the bottles
because there was no interest and I
also got cheated, so I said that
I will not be able to commit to selling, I will do farming, I will
live a simple life, I don't want to get into the trap of all this.
Almost everyone said something or the other.
Do something, why are you sitting idle, do some
work, get some job done, do something,
relatives also said, neighbors also
said, everyone said but my mother did
not say do something, she said
do whatever you like and we will do it.
take whatever we want, whatever we have to earn, we will
do it, you sit comfortably, study,
do whatever you like,
then he basically knew the meaning behind the
scenes, meaning I am not doing anything wrong,
watch some picture or movie.
working on myself, I was doing well in English, I would do
something one day, so he had
faith in me that I would do something, that is
why he never asked me to
do any job or to work or to study.
My mother did not force me to do anything, except her, that is, except
my family,
everyone else told me to do something, do something, so my
aunt has a school, a school till 10th, a
school from first to 10th.
Our aunt's son has a school there, basically he said I have to
teach in the school, I
said first I don't want to
teach, then he said teach, meaning
he knew that I teach well,
basically Ashish bhaiya, his name is Ashish.
Bhaiya said, he knew that I
teach well, I have also taught coaching,
so he said, try teaching, come and
see how you like it, then later, if you
don't feel like teaching, then don't teach, just try.
Then he said.
started teaching there, it felt right, I taught
there for a year, I taught
science and maths to children from six to 10, I used to
teach English also,
sometimes if the English teacher did not come,
but my main subject was
was science and maths, but even when I was teaching, there was that
emptiness inside that something has to be done,
something should be done, that emptiness was always there,
meaning it did not feel that we have to live our entire
life like this, this is our life, this is
our job.
felt that something was missing and something should be done.
Meanwhile, when I was teaching in school,
I met my wife through social media. At
that time, I did not have a wife, but today,
she is a wife and
felt good to meet him, the mind set was
quite similar, interest in spirituality, interest in
maths, interest in science, interest in
physics, all these interests were similar,
meaning same and many other things were similar, goal was to
do something good, meaning in a
way, it meant me.
in the female version, it was ok, I felt that we started
talking and I liked it a lot and
then he pushed me to do something,
so he showed me the opportunity that
many things
can be done through the internet.
Many people do jobs on the internet. Earlier, I did
not think that I could
get something through the internet. Although I used to use the internet, I did
not think that much about the job,
so my only conventional method
was
get a job from there, so I knew this path,
he said that no, there are other things,
so I thought what to do now, so I
thought, let's do 3D
modeling, so I did it because he
is my brother.
Adarsh. He was already doing 3D modeling. I had introduced him to 3D modeling.
I had also taught him coding for 3D modeling.
When I did not know it,
I had provided him tutorials.
He had also learned it but he also had
was no guidance as to what to do next, how to
get a job in it or some of the
things she knew but she knew coding, C language,
Python, she knew all these things but she also did
not know what to do next and
ended by solving only that many questions.
modeling and making models, so
I thought, let's do 3D modeling, it will bring
something, that is, I will
do some freelancing online on Upwork, on Fiber,
I learned a little bit of freelancing,
not much, just not freelancing,
basically did not learn much of 3D modeling.
created an account on Upwork
that I am a freelance
3D designer, I make 3D models,
so we got a client from the US, we got a
client, he got the design of a car
made, the design of the car must be lying somewhere,
if you can find the link of it.
was YouTube1 but I thought
how long will this work continue, I learn it myself, so
my brother completed the first project,
I used to just talk
in between that I have to do this, he completed the entire
project and
dollars, more than 100, 100, 50 dollars
and the first income was through online,
so I did not do everything in it,
I just talked, then after that
I learned D myself and made models by myself.
But I was not enjoying it, I was
not feeling any meaning in it that this is not what I am doing, this is
our life, we will spend it in this only and that too
means I made models again, one ad,
maybe one for the same client, one freelancing for some other client
and so on.
but I earned the same 100 50 00 through that
but I did
not get any feeling in it either, it did not feel very right, still
I used to learn 3D modeling from
youtube0 modeling, so one day I was
watching a video of 3D modeling.
ad coming, that ad was of a web development course
and in that ad a lady was speaking, she was
saying something and I liked her way of speaking
that how we will
learn, how each and every thing was covered.
Within this course, I thought that let's try
web development once again,
I purchased that course and the
price of that course was only ₹ 5000000
and this day was the turning point of my life,
from then on there was no looking back, it was so good.
He taught me web development, it was very easy to
understand, beginner friendly, he explained everything very well and
after that my life
changed completely, I started understanding every concept of web development, I got
interested.
HTML, CSS,
JavaScript, React and whatever he
covered in the notes, so I followed all the things
and I
practiced a lot of CSS, my CSS
became very good, I started creating responses very easily
and
taught me, it was very basic and
I tried to learn CSS well,
after that I made many projects using CSS,
basically
in the beginning I focused on CSS only,
many projects of CSS.
projects on my own, he
said do you know CSS, I said
yes, he said if you give me some design then you will make it, he
sent the design, I said
yes, we will make it, he said,
how much will you charge for making a design, then
I said, I have it in my mind.
make such projects every day,
I can do this for free but if they are
asking then they will say something, then I
said, I will take 5500, I said, ok, ok, do it,
they sent it to me,
what project do I want to make?
was nothing much, just a few cards, the
design was a bit complicated, that is why he knew
little CSS, that is why he took my help, so I did
that and gave it to him
and he gave me another project,
then I did both the projects.
Both were simple projects, I did the
project in about two to four days
and they gave me Rs. 000 because there was
talk of Rs. 50000 for one project, they gave me Rs. 1000 and
I earned Rs. 000 in four days. This is
my first freelancing project.
That I did not reach out, it was
they who did the reach out. It was
Instagram's freelancing project, so
I thought, okay, I am starting to get the hang of
freelancing, so I am in all the
social media groups, the
Discord groups of the tubers.
then in some discord, someone
messaged that is there any front end developer, is
he needed? So I said, I
messaged him that yes, I know, so
he hired me, that is,
he gave me some
projects.
earned Rs 56000. There were not many big projects, there
were only small projects, so
there I got Rs 000 from him and then
one more and one more. Basically,
I did a project for a startup and
got Rs 4,000 for that too.
from web development, I thought let's
go to Bangalore, I got a little confidence
that I am getting some money from this and
I am also feeling good, so the confidence came,
let's go to Bangalore and I will get a job there.
got something then I came, meaning there
was no job now, I just came like this, did one or two
freelancing projects and then came
here, I started applying for internships,
I thought I
would get only internships, what else can I get with so much knowledge?
I applied for internship at many places and got a
call from many places. Basically,
I got a call from one place. They said that we have an
opening for internship but we
need a freelancer. If you
do freelancing then you can work for us.
Basically he did not have any team, it was more of a
project, he had got it done
from a developer, the project was fine but he was
well versed in responsiveness, I knew the lead well, I had
prepared a lot of responses, he
said yes, I will do it, so I
asked him.
I said, I will take Rs. 500 for an hour, meaning Rs.
500 for an hour. I said no, this is too much.
He said that we can give Rs. 00. I was
thinking in my mind that Rs. 00 for an hour is quite
good, it means I did Rs. 500 for an hour a day.
they said that we
can give Rs. 200. I said that it is okay, I will do the
work, it doesn't matter that you are speaking for the first time,
I will do it. I was happy from inside, so I
decided on another hour.
started working on their website,
although I had come to Bangalore, there was no job at that time, it
was only freelancing work, so
I worked for about 28 or 20 25 days for a month,
25 to 28 days, I worked on it
and
was a good payment, that is, I had worked for more than 100 hours, so when they paid me around
Rs. 0000, it
felt even better. I felt
confident that this is the work of my choice,
which I can do for free, and
get paid for it.
freelancing project was over now,
now I started applying for internship again
and I applied to many places at
least 20 times a day,
then I started getting calls.
my interview was scheduled. In the interview,
they asked something like JavaScript, Single
Threaded, Multi Threaded. Well,
I had not studied it, it was
not mentioned in the course. Angela said, "
What is this, okay?" She said, "I have
said, I guess I had heard about single threaded
somewhere in some video, so I said,
what does it mean when I say single threaded?
I said, now I have to explain its meaning also,
I said, I don't know all this, then
asked one or two more questions.
core concepts of JavaScript, so I did
n't know anything. I said, "Hey,
what have you read? I have followed the entire course
from you, Angela, so I don't know it at all,
then I have
come to Realix S. I
don't know JavaScript, just a little."
ifs for loops and functions but I do
n't know JavaScript well. So what should I
do now? Then I purchased their Colt
Steel course.
I saw only the JavaScript section
and their JavaScript was quite good
Anjala.
JavaScript was much more detailed, it was bigger
and they explained it a little better, so
from there I got a little
better knowledge of JavaScript, I
understood it more completely, the whole whole picture was understood, the fundamental
concepts were clear, but still I was not ready for
the interviews.
I was getting stuck in JavaScript. People were
asking closures, hidden functions
and scopes, meaning how does lexic
scope work, what is all this, synchronous,
how is synchronous code running,
call backs.
interns ask. Okay, it was still
not happening, so when I was following Cold Steel
in JavaScript course,
here when I came to Bangalore,
a friend of mine became a person.
settled here in Bangalore.
He is also working today. His name is
Gautam, so he is also working in front end.
When we met, we were learning together,
so I used to help him.
He helped me to settle down in Bangalore.
He is from Bangalore and he
sent me a course called Namaste JavaScript by Akshay Saini. At
that time I
was not ready to watch that course. I saw
that he was teaching something.
going on top that at that time I had
studied Anjala U and I was not able to understand
what they were teaching, everyone was
teaching useless things, I said this is a bad course,
it is not a very good course, so I
n't even see it, then I
read JavaScript from Colt Steel. When my
JavaScript became good, then I
saw it again. When I saw it again, my eyes opened. Suddenly
JavaScript seemed cool. I
understood everything. He wrote it very
well. Akshay.
very well in the Namaste JavaScript series,
how JavaScript works behind the scenes. I started
understanding everything
and I thought
that it means do some other advanced courses too,
I have done
YouTube's but in that advanced course
also.
taught, Namaste, the
same things were there in JavaScript too, so
basically I understood it twice and it was repeated,
so whatever advanced concepts were behind the
scenes, how JavaScript works,
because of Akshay Saini and
because of JavaScript, my JavaScript became
very good. I started understanding JavaScript on my own by digging into
their dev tools more than what they taught me. They
explained me
how to use the dev tools, so effectively,
after that I learned it on my own.
exploring on my own, understood JavaScript in depth,
after that my interview started
going well and I got selected in a startup. If
yes, then how was the selection,
I also tell you in my resume
what is my education.
not there, so in one of the sections at the bottom,
I had mentioned that
under education, I had seen some courses like Self-Tut, UD and Coursera, but
from Coursera,
although I had seen some courses not of web development but of Ed,
sometimes that's it.
Self Tut UD course, that's all I had
mentioned, Free Quote Cam was also probably mentioned, I do
n't remember, this is what I had mentioned,
so when the interviewers used to call, it was
pickle call or interviewer's
call.
that when did you do graduation and
in which field, I used to say that
I have not done graduation,
I learned coding after 10th and I was interested in it,
so I did it after 10th.
doing web development and freelancing
and these are some of my freelancing
projects which I have done
inside the resume. Inside the resume, I had done my
original freelancing projects
which were two-three projects, they
were all projects and one
projects were just one or two such personal
projects, so in the resume also,
I had also made a portfolio, that
portfolio is quite good, it is still there, I will
give its link in the description, if you
go and see it, then I have made one named Anug sbm.com.
domain and on top of that I had
hosted my portfolio, on top of that
I had
kept whatever freelancing projects I had, so I had told
that I mean I used to tell the interviewer that
I learned web development after 10th and learned
coding.
okay, I am freelancing, these are
some of my projects, okay, so they used to
say, okay, no problem, skill matters to us,
degree does not matter that much,
and to my surprise,
I got about 20 interviewers.
which only one said that
we want a B.Tech person, sorry we can't proceed with you, it's
okay, the one with degree,
then after listening to all the others said that
skill matters to us, degree does
n't matter to us.
n't know if this happens to everyone,
otherwise I feel that my
projects and my freelancing
work were good, my portfolio
was good, that's what people were saying after seeing it.
That it is working well, so it does
n't matter, the degree doesn't matter, if
you just go straight like this, we will speak, we know
nothing just by speaking, you have to show the
work, so it may not happen with you.
If your portfolio is strong,
your resume is strong, the projects are
good and if there are freelancing
projects then there are more chances of
your getting selected, so
I think that is why he was saying
that this guy knows, he has done the work.
we don't care about degree, we care
about skill and if you know it then you will be
selected. If you give interview
then interview was scheduled and I
gave many interviews and got selected at some two or three places
and there was a company whose name was
Digit.
interview and I performed very well,
I answered about 80-90 questions, mainly it was on
JavaScript, there were
a few questions, so
I answered
and I got selected there. Okay, I
also got marks in the company.
but I found Digit to be a very good company,
their brand ambassador was Virat Kohli, so it was
nice to see him and it was a big
company, it had a good product base,
so I decided to join there
and that was my first company.
I am very thankful to the first interviewer who got selected
because he
valued my skills and he
gave me a chance. I joined Digit Insurance on 22 July 2021
and my
position there was Software Engineer
and when I got this position, I was
was no limit to my happiness after that as my father had said that
I had become a software engineer and
people who were coming after doing B.Tech, M.Tech or BC MCA were
sitting next to me.
and there was no difference in salary wise, the
salary was the same as theirs, mine was the same,
respect is the same, everything is there and
people were respecting me a little more
because I had learned it myself.
Everyone there knew that this guy is self-
taught, he has studied only after 10th, so
my experience inside Digit was very good, there was a
very good team, there was a very friendly team, there were
very good and supportive managers, I
never got any help from anyone inside Digit.
not have to face anything like politics, I used to do my work.
Within my job, I worked only on
HTML, CSS and JavaScript, which means
basically I mainly worked on CSS and JavaScript. For
2 years, I
worked only on CSS and JavaScript.
Because of this, my JavaScript and
CSS became stronger and the core
technologies became stronger and I knew
my work so well.
I knew JavaScript CS
so well that in two years
worked and never needed help from any senior.
Whatever problem came,
I used to figure it out on my own.
Whatever, if there is any back end
problem, any other technology problem, with
whom.
I need to take help from others.
I did not need to take help from anyone for my work. So
if your fundamental
concept is clear then
you can solve the problem on your own.
know what the problem is, then when
you remain like this, you have
a respect within the company, you are a good person,
people come and ask you, people used to
think that I have a lot of
experience, so whatever there is
ask me, if there is any
problem with JavaScript, they used to ask me only,
even though I am doing it for the first time, I
am less junior than them, which means I have
less experience than them, still they used to
come and ask me and I was like them.
because my fundamental
concepts were clear, my CSS and
JavaScript were clear, that is why I did
not face any problem in two years
because my work was always clean, I used to complete my
entire work in four-five hours,
after that
then after 5:00 pm I started
playing table tennis.
After 5:30 pm I used to go to play TT and for one year
we played a lot of TT, meaning two, two, three-
hours means I played a lot of TT and my TT had also become
very good and
no one has any problem because my work is always ready, that is,
whatever work is given,
I keep it working, so when you
know things well.
your work gets done very fast, you are
not stuck anywhere, if you face any problem, you will come to
know that it is a problem, it is
very rare, I don't even remember
that I ever got stuck
on any problem.
problem gets solved immediately. You should know how to
use Google3 well,
so now Chat GPT has come, earlier
Chat GPT was not there, the only
thing I missed is that this is my first
youtube in 1 or 18.
or 20, I had started teaching Math on
YouTube1. I had
tried making a chain once before, so this is
not my first time. After
making three videos on YouTube2, I
lost my motivation and stopped it because
in
meaning I had not done anything myself, what would
I teach to others, so that
confidence was not coming from within, even though
I knew the topics, I knew maths,
but there was a hollow feeling from within.
youtube4 was not closed at that time, my
youtube2 was closed after uploading three videos,
so then I mean it was always in my mind
that on
youtube4, on September 2022, I
uploaded the first video and then on September 10,
2000 22, I uploaded my first video.
and started teaching,
I covered everything very well, whatever
I knew, I had one year of company
experience,
I learned all the things from different courses, I studied
CSS, taught JavaScript and
Then in between everything was going well and it was
growing normally at its own pace. Then
in between we got married. If you will
see some videos of JavaScript set
time out and in the videos of that particular time,
then you will see in my hand.
seen wearing mehendi, then at that time, in the middle of the time, when the
JavaScript project i.e. videos were
going on, the playlist was going on, then
in the middle, we got married and we got settled here in
Bangalore and then everything was going well on
youtube0.
almost 2023, it was 2023, that
means two years were about to go inside Digit and
I was starting to find some work boring, which was
office work because it was the same HTML, CSS
and JavaScript, on top of that
I was
meaning there was not much new left,
almost the same work was to be done every day, there was
no React in my company, which was a digital
insurance company, Angular was used there,
so I said that Angular was used.
Give us some projects, we will learn Angular, so
I learned Angular,
after learning Angular, I took some Angular projects.
What does project mean, small features, feature
additions, bugs, all this,
I did two or three things, but still
I have to do regular projects with Angular.
I was mainly getting only CSS and
JavaScript projects for
which I had worked for two years and it was
starting to get a bit boring. Now I mean,
Angular projects were not found there, so
I thought let's try somewhere else.
good if I find it somewhere, where
I can work in React because
React was my favorite framework and I had
learned React well,
so I created my profile on Well Found, whose name
was earlier Angel List, and that's it,
I shared my
experience.
Well Found and then from there I got a
message from there itself asking, are
you available for the job, is it open?
So I said yes, I am open
and there in my report also.
also got the resume from there, so basically
it was a UK based company, from there a
UK guy had reached out to me,
so I said yes, I am available,
he said notice period, you mentioned 30 days
in your resume.
period is 30 days, I said no, it
is 30 days, not three months, they said,
then why did you mention 30 days,
I said, then the call will not come, if you mention 90
days, you will mention three months, then the call will
not come at all, you reach.
so I mentioned it like this and he
started laughing and said, ok, no problem, let's
do your interview, we will
see you later, we will wait
or whatever happens, it will be seen, then he
scheduled the interview.
-Different
round was conducted, questions were asked very well, questions were
taken in depth, I
liked the interview very much, I also performed well,
I answered 90 questions
and I got selected here, then
I told my rejection in my old company.
Resign Resign
Resigned, submitted my resignation letter,
then after three months, I
joined my current company, whose name is
DS Plus, now I work here
even today and this company of ours
is completely remote, so I am still working there.
itself and everything is going well,
life is good, I am
living like any software engineer earns, I am living like that, there is
no problem but there are still a lot of things to do
as I wanted to study but
not get the resources, I did not find any good teacher
due to which a lot of my
time was wasted, at one time I found a good teacher
and then I was able to study, so I
believe that almost every child wants to study,
basically most of the children want to study,
some
want to study, if they are not able to study, then there is
lack of main resources, there is
lack of good teachers, so my goal is
that if any child wants to learn web development,
then he should not feel the lack of resources.
Yes, it should be easy to learn and in
depth in details, just
like two plus two is four,
we have no doubt in this, similarly if
someone teaches web development then it will
be as clear as two plus two is four.
that way, only when there is clarity,
you are able to do something, then that clarity
is important and presence of a good teacher is important.
Presence of a good course is
important, that is why I have made my complete front end
course of 148 145 hours.
course is a long course, it will take time, if you
follow it, it may take 6 to 8 months, it may
even take 9 months,
depending on how much you can learn
in a day, if you follow that course.
complete it completely, then you
can also get a job as an Experience Developer, that is, you
can also get an interview for an Experience Developer,
I have covered so many things well there, I have
made and completed the entire course of Front End on
our
youtube3.
course is needed by many children in our country. There are
many children in India
who want to learn but they are not
getting the right course, are
not getting the right guidance, are not getting the right teacher.
If so, share this course as much as possible,
this channel with your friends or
children who are
interested in learning web development.
Tell them about this course
so that they can learn well what they want to learn.
Get it and if any
doubt comes while learning then I do it live on Google3 every Sunday from
8 pm to 11:00 pm
and I sit for about 3 hours and
any child can come and ask his/her doubts there for free.
All the children come
every day, we do this every Sunday, from
8 to 12 in the night, anyone can join the G Meet and
ask their doubts for free and
we have a Telegram group where
children help each other.
anyone can join that group who is
learning and can take help from other children and
clear their doubts, so
this is my attempt to do
something for our country, such children who are helpless.
who are not getting the course, are
not getting the right teacher, this course should
reach them and they should be able to learn, this is just my
effort from my side, let me make one thing
clear here that if my course is free then only
free courses are good.
teach for free or those who teach for free are good, those
who teach paid courses are bad, it is
not so, whoever is the
instructor, whoever is teaching through paid courses
or is teaching for free, howsoever he
is teaching, all are good.
learned is that my life has changed because of a paid
course, so it does not happen
that if someone is making a paid course then he is a
scam. Never
look at a paid course and call it a scam, it is okay.
I have learned from paid courses only, I have
taken many paid courses, if you
cannot afford that course it means simply
that course is not for you, okay if you
can afford it comfortably then that course
is for you.
made this entire course for free, so
anyone can access it, now anyone
can access it, the down side of this is
that many people will start and
leave in the middle because of some commitment.
Nothing will be left for them, no, if someone
starts a paid course after watching it, then at
least because of the money, he keeps learning.
My motivation for making this course is
that if any child in our country
wants to learn web development.
due to lack of resources, he should never have the
feeling of being helpless, just like I had the
feeling once when I had to
learn Physics, I was
not able to find any good teacher, no one was explaining it well,
that feeling of helplessness.
is very bad, so my
goal is that this course should reach every child,
I will give you the link of this course
in the description of the video and if you
follow my course, you
will notice one thing that I never
n't say like share subscribe in any video
because I don't like it, I find it
a bit distracting, I have
not come here to like share subscribe, I will
get that, I don't have it, I
find it distracting, basically it
doesn't suit me.
bell icon, till date I have never said
share subscribe in any video,
maybe I say comment comment in some comment, if there
is any doubt then you can ask by commenting
but share subscribe in every video
people like
come, then the force bell will come, then it will ring,
press the bell on this, I never say all this,
so it does not mean that you do not have to
support, whatever you can do,
you support.
course should reach the children in some way, no matter
how they download it, whatever they do, they
watch it. I don't care about likes, shares, subscriptions or
views, just that it should reach them so that
they know that there is something like this.
keep it in my local and watch it, I will not
get views. It doesn't matter whether I download it or
watch it, the only thing that matters to me is
that any child who
is helpless, who is in need, should go to this course.
How can it be done without a degree.
and now I am working on
youtube2. If you are in any adverse session,
but if you get good guidance, you get a
good course, you
get a good teacher and if you have the
passion to learn, that is commitment.
meet me in your course
till then bye bye